<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-21T17:06:17-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Market Ramblings</title><subtitle>Random Market Notes</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Markets are Organisms</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/markets-are-organisms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Markets are Organisms" /><published>2021-01-21T16:41:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T16:41:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/markets-are-organisms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/markets-are-organisms.html">&lt;p&gt;What the market is least prepared for, it will get. Expect the unexpected. When very
few expect a correction a correction will be sufficient to disrupt sentiment. When a correction
is expected, a correction won’t do the job any more than a surprise party will surprise you
when someone has told  you that it’s going to happen. So the question becomes what will retrain
the market? This is precisely what makes figuring where the markets are headed such a difficult
task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that markets operate as a single organism comprised of billions of individual cells.
Over time the organism experiences different episodes, some very traumatic. When these things
happen, the organism is on especially high guard for a similar occurrence. Then, after enough time
has passed, it let’s its guard down. The old cells have been replaced with younger, less experienced
cells. This leaves the organism susceptible to new shocks, both to the upside and downside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a period of extreme volatility and bear markets many will expect new bear markets on every
big advance only to be dismayed as it keeps moving higher. This current market is even more challenging
because things seem to happen in hyper-speed. But sometimes the simplest explanation is the best
one and indeed I think we may be over complicating the current market. It’s likely not a new normal
in which valuation has no place and businesses need not make more than they spend. This bull simply
has further to run as more and more converts move from skeptical to bullish. It’s race is not yet
run and the time for rampant bearishness isn’t upon us. Eventually though cash levels deplete,
negative fundamental factors present themselves amid extreme sentiment, and the collapse begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prove this out, think back on every significant correction and crash across every market over
the past twenty years- the dot-com bubble, the real estate crash and great recession, volmageddon, the bear market and swift recovery in Q4 of 2018 into 2019- each one of these with minimal exception
caught the market for the most part completely off sides. Of course with each there were a few lone
voices calling for impending doom, but even many of these were permabears or gold bugs always looking for doom in every setup. But for the most part, the market was not expecting what came next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the current market I feel there is still just too much skepticism for a major crash to come right
away, and this is something I have been saying for a month or two now. Having been incorrectly bearish from August on, expecting a crash I realize in hindsight I was way early. But now in recent weeks I
have heard more and more calls for a crash and the end of this speculative episode once and for all,
with many calling for a 10% correction or so in January which would present a buying opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Precisely because the market is so comfortable with this outcome, I believe that either any correction will not end with 10% downside followed by another massive rally to new highs, but finally be the correction that ushers in a lasting, painful bear market as virtually nobody seems to expect this as a possibility. Or, more likely, the market continues higher for a longer period of perhaps another 2-4 months before finally breaking down. It’s hard to say. I still lean very bearish due to the extreme positioning, speculation, and P/E ratios which I hear more and more discounting as an outdated metric! But fighting the tape is recipe for disaster so patience is the only play for now. However I still expect any significant crash to start gradually so I don’t believe it’s necessary to get aggressively positioned early as very few expect a drawn out bear market in any area possible given Fed policy. Plus, the fact that every correction of consequence of the last several years has been immediately bought up, leading to a complacency that is unrivaled in my memory. By complacency I mean a market that is ready to discount any correction as healthy and a buying opportunity. However there are many warning flags I’ve mentioned ad nauseam here- the ARK/retail feedback loop, excessive call buying, and absurd SPAC growth. I am content to follow the tape from here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last note- I do find the price action in megacap tech over the past few days to be interesting. After doing nothing since the end of August, and frustrating the permabulls to no end, and permabulls remaining convinced that they were right and the tape wrong, and continuing to buy these stocks, seemingly out of the blue, the megacaps finally complied with their wishes and have had an extraordinary rally over the past few days. This is interesting to me because as I talk about often, when dumb money consensus wants something to happen desperately, that thing seldom if ever happens. I feel then, that this price action could be one last trap in a blow off top for the market to build even more confidence in the retail crowd. To explain the movement, Netflix had blowout earnings earlier this week and I feel that this rally is late money positioning for earnings and not much else. Megacap after earnings will be interesting to watch and will likely offer some clues as to what comes next.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What the market is least prepared for, it will get. Expect the unexpected. When very few expect a correction a correction will be sufficient to disrupt sentiment. When a correction is expected, a correction won’t do the job any more than a surprise party will surprise you when someone has told you that it’s going to happen. So the question becomes what will retrain the market? This is precisely what makes figuring where the markets are headed such a difficult task.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finally, a Decent Setup</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/14/finally-a-decent-setup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finally, a Decent Setup" /><published>2021-01-14T14:14:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T14:14:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/14/finally-a-decent-setup</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/14/finally-a-decent-setup.html">&lt;p&gt;I haven’t been trading at all for the past month or so, mostly because I simply haven’t spotted any setups that were remotely favorable. I know my style and it’s not chasing MOMO stocks or very short-term smallish movements. I tend to try to spot longer term trend changes, mostly tops that will begin lengthy or significant downtrends. Obviously given the current market trends it has been difficult to be overly bearish, so I’ve found myself in a sort of purgatory where I don’t want to chase anything on the long side, but am afraid to go short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That changed today when I finally spotted a setup that fit my criteria. Now I just entered a very small trade today to test it out, so I have no idea if it will prove to be profitable or not, but I did want to take the time to explain the setup and why I found it to be favorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stock in question is AMD. For many months, AMD has been a major public favorite and the move in it has not disappointed, having more than doubled in less than a year. This is a stock that I view as highly speculative because most who offer fundamental analysis have little actual understanding of the chip space and parrot the obvious bullish factors that everyone has known for many months. Last week, it broke up towards $100 and it looked as if it was on the verge of a massive breakout. But then it quickly reversed lower towards $95. Then earlier this week, news broke that Intel was going to replace its CEO. This caused Intel stock to immediately rip higher, and AMD to drop significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immediate, obvious reaction from the bulls was that it was stupid to sell AMD given that Intel was years behind and even if the new CEO was effective it would take years to turn the company around. Now, for what it’s worth, I actually agree with this. I think Intel has major, systemic problems that are going to be close to impossible to fix. But what I think doesn’t matter. While I’m long-term bearish on Intel, and I know that just a couple of years ago I would have fallen for this setup and quickly stepped in to buy up AMD on the dip, I now believe that you really have to carefully consider the opposite side of the trade and not immediately assume that your counter-party is a complete ignoramus who doesn’t have access to the same information you do. Of course they do. They have better information than you do. So then you must consider, in spite of all this, why are they selling? Or why aren’t more people buying? There must be a reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past day or two, while AMD stock has continued to dip lower, the bulls have continued to confidently cite this price action as a major buying opportunity. It’s important to remember that sometimes stretched stocks are looking for a reason to sell off and don’t need a great one, any will do to disrupt the upward trend. I think that could be where AMD is. Most of the market is extremely bullish on it which makes the risk/reward to going long given the failed breakout and now continued weakness pretty bad, IMO, which makes the short setup pretty compelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I continue to say, some of the best selloff catalysts are wolves in sheep’s clothing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I haven’t been trading at all for the past month or so, mostly because I simply haven’t spotted any setups that were remotely favorable. I know my style and it’s not chasing MOMO stocks or very short-term smallish movements. I tend to try to spot longer term trend changes, mostly tops that will begin lengthy or significant downtrends. Obviously given the current market trends it has been difficult to be overly bearish, so I’ve found myself in a sort of purgatory where I don’t want to chase anything on the long side, but am afraid to go short.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blow-Off Rallies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/blow-off-rallies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blow-Off Rallies" /><published>2021-01-08T15:01:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-08T15:01:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/blow-off-rallies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/08/blow-off-rallies.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve read most of the well-known books about stock picking/trading/investing. The one I find
myself going back to more than any other is Marty Zweig’s &lt;i&gt;Winning on Wall Street.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite part of the book is the introduction, in which Zweig recounts how he famously
predicted the 1987 stock market crash. I think the information presented in those few pages is a timeless reminder of how the largest crashes in recent history have occurred and how similar conditions appear in the lead-ups. One particular part I always
come back to when things seem extra frothy is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;What bothered me were the similarites to 1929, 1946, and 1962. The familiar pattern was gross overvaluation in P/E&apos;s and yields along with straight-up price movement which lacked a major correction for years and which had produced doubles or a lot more in the Dow. When these conditions had existed, I found that, late in bull markets, there was a major rally lasting several months which evolved out of a minor correction (the one which started in the fall of 1986 at 1755), another minor correction (spring of 1987 from 2404 to 2216), then a narrow smaller blowoff rally to the final high lasting 2-3 months (which peaked this time in August at 2722).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Those earlier markets then began what looked like &quot;normal&quot; corrections, but which soon cascaded into breaks. The key, and what upset me in September, was that as the smaller correction unfurled, the sentiment on Wall Street was &quot;buy &apos;em.&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that last part is particularly informative because indeed it has been my experience that the worst selloffs come as wolves in sheep’s clothing. Bull markets work people over time into an attitude of overconfidence, complacency, and the expectation that if anything at all were to sink the market, it would have to be something REALLY big like a terrorist attack or the Fed hiking rates 4% without warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is folly. History shows us that in old bull markets when things really get extended, it takes very little to upset the market. The trouble for the bulls is that they have now formed a world view that people selling on such a small news item (Roger Babson in 1929, Kennedy’s comments regarding the steel industry in 1962, or the Fed hiking a single time in 1987) must be ill-informed and that they will be happy to take the idiot bears’ shares off their hands at such a bargain price. In these circumstances, stock prices no longer have any relation to fundamentals, they are just traded on a basis relative to prior highs. Amazon at anything under $3000 must be a bargain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While reading the previous quote from Marty Zweig last week and observing the price action in the market over the past couple of weeks I have a strong suspicion that we are at the doorstep of a crash. In Zweig’s account, he cites the Dow. Everyone has their own opinions of the indices and their relevance. Mine is that the Dow was the index that mattered in a prior time. But in the past ten years or so, the Nasdaq has replaced it as the major indicator of the market’s strength. You can also use the S&amp;amp;P if you like (as most do), as it’s market cap weighting allocates most of its weighting to the same few primary constituents that carry most of the NASDAQ, hence the very close correlation in these over the past few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at a chart of the past year, you can see that the crash of February/March of 2020 looks a lot more like a correction in the rear view, albeit a major one. Then in September through October we got another, smaller correction. After the election in November, the market began rallying violently with the small caps and average stocks carrying the slack that the mega cap tech names gave up after the September correction. Given the extreme exuberance among the Bitcoin, Tesla, growth stock and SPAC crowd, I have a feeling we are in this last, narrow 2-3 month blow-off rally Zweig referred to in his analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 1929, right before the markets made their final top, many stocks doubled in a period of just a few months after having experienced a small correction in March. $TSLA, $MSTR, $BTC, $ROKU, $PTON, $IPOC (or $IPOE or $IPOF or all of them) have doubled or more since the middle of November (less than two months)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the time is drawing near for a major crash that will likely hit tech stocks the hardest but won’t spare any sector. I also believe Bitcoin will crash if this happens, as has happened in every major correction we’ve had in the past few years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final point. A normal question to raise at this take would be “but what about stimulus and the Fed?” Those are obviously bullish factors, but only to a point. At some point equities become too stretched and positioning too aggressive. This is when markets are at their weakest, and to reiterate the earlier point, it takes very little to unseat the market. Once markets begin a downtrend at these levels, they can become panicky very quickly, in a reverse feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know about stimulus. We all know about the Fed. And we are all trying to take each other’s money in the market. So at some point you have to part company with the common narrative that everything is bullish. I believe we’re at a point where pretty much anything could cause an initial break. One recent potential factor is interest rates which have started moving up recently and just crossed 1% yesterday. Interestingly, I heard Kevin O’Leary say just today on CNBC that it would require rates above 3% to impact equities. In the same introduction from &lt;i&gt;Winning on Wall Street&lt;/i&gt; that I cited at the beginning of this post, Zweig wrote that leading up the the 1987 crash most were insistent that the Fed would have to hike rates at least three times for the market to take note. The first and only hike happened in August of 1987.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve written in my past couple of entries, what I’m looking for is a downward trend to begin on a seemingly innocuous catalyst. Nobody can say what this will be. But the tell-tale sign will be the bulls completely writing off the catalyst as a nothingburger while the market continues down. There will be rallies along the way to assuage the bulls’ concerns and allow them to get trapped further. I believe this setup will be an unbelievably favorable risk reward for near dated out of the money puts on most anything. In my prior post I talked about Intel and IBM which I still think would be great put plays due to their low IV. However I am becoming more and more enamored with the idea of ARKK, as that is as clear a bubble as I have seen in some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure I will have more to say on this over the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve read most of the well-known books about stock picking/trading/investing. The one I find myself going back to more than any other is Marty Zweig’s Winning on Wall Street.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Market Outlook for 2021</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/05/market-outlook-for-2021.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Market Outlook for 2021" /><published>2021-01-05T16:39:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-05T16:39:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/05/market-outlook-for-2021</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/05/market-outlook-for-2021.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;All crises have involved debt that, in one fashion or another, has become dangerously out of scale in relation to the underlying means of payment. More often, even a semblance of innovation is absent. In the 1920s, as we shall see, great holding companies were created. The owners, that is to say the stockholders, issued bonds and preferred stock in order to buy other stocks. As the latter appreciated in value- for a while- all the increase accrued to the owners. This was proclaimed one of the financial miracles of that age. It was, in fact, leverage in, at most, a slightly different guise.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;-John Kenneth Galbraith, A Short History of Financial Euphoria&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In late cycle bull markets you start to see strange things crop up. I was reading the above excerpt last night and couldn’t help but immediately think of the rise of ARK Invest and how Cathie Wood, the founder, is widely cited as a genius stock picker and tech visionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I subscribe to a few schools of thought when it comes to the market, maybe the most important being that when opportunity is present, many are drawn in, few survive, and even fewer thrive. It is a sad fact of life that there can only be a few true visionaries- Edison, Jobs, Ford, etc. When you start to see many people cited as genius visionaries at once, there’s a good chance there’s some willful delusion at play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I felt it appropriate to start this piece with that excerpt is that I think it serves as a strong reminder that when bubbles are in effect, people are willing to part with reason and things that they probably fundamentally understand about the world at some level. Cathie Wood is 65 years old. She founded ARK in 2014, roughly six years ago as I write this. ARK really seemed to hit its stride when Tesla’s stock started moving up. ARK continued to be perfectly positioned to ride the growth stock ascent. As ARK’s reputation (and the price of its stock holdings) rose, it launched more ETF’s. So what’s happening now is that you have investors buying stock in an ETF run by someone with a reputation as a visionary, which then uses said inflows to buy shares of high-flying growth stocks, which, after it being reported that ARK has initiated or increased its stake, rise as a result, further lifting the shares of ARK’s ETF’s in a virtuous feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has all the makings of a bubble within a bubble. One can hardly deny that there is at least massive correlation at play here where ARK’s success is closely tied to Tesla’s share price and the growth stock complex as well as investors’ seemingly insatiable appetite for risky stock issues. If you peruse any Twitter thread in which someone asks the question “what stocks are best to buy right now?” You will almost certainly see the majority of responses mention ARKK, the ARK Innovation ETF. It is consensus in the retail crowd that this is not only a smart investment, but should really be a cornerstone of any responsible portfolio. And this is not hyperbole. I read comments like this about once a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the ingredients are here for a market top- overnight visionaries who’s star has risen with the market. Wood is not a lone exception, there are many others. One example being Chamath Palihapitya who has recently gotten fully involved with the SPAC craze, launching something like five or six SPAC’s in the past year. As the public has bought these up hand over fist, Chamath has become quite arrogant and unshy about promoting his own genius, despite not having much in the way of wins beyond a successful exit as an early employee at Facebook and selling shares to the public in businesses that at best, have yet to show sustained success at actually operating as a going concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other problem signs- mega cap tech stocks look to have topped in early September prior to the correction that occurred around that time. Even though they certainly haven’t been in a down trend, their character has completely changed from leading the bull advance to simply treading water on low volume. I’ve seen many assume that this is a healthy consolidation, forming a nice long base that will resolve with a massive rally to the upside. And why shouldn’t they? The past five years have engrained in investor’s minds that every dip should be bought. I believe there is a very important time element in markets to wash away widespread fear and skepticism born in a lengthy painful bear market to setup for another. While we have had minute corrections from time to time, none have lasted more than a few months and in every case though doubts persisted early about how wise it was to buy the dip, history showed that if you had done so on any of those you’d be up significantly a few months later. I think we are at a point now where the bulls have enough confidence in their abilities and delusion about the lack of basic need for a company to earn more money than it spends to setup for a devastating bear market. The question is, what would that look like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have heard it consistently said that the market won’t really go down until the Fed tightens again which isn’t likely to be for at least a couple of years. The latter part of this I agree with. I do not, however agree with the premise that you can’t have a bear market emerge with a Fed as unambiguously accommodative as this one. The Fed’s positioning in 2019 and 2020 gave rise to a market that was completely unconcerned about Fed policy. This has led to extraordinarily stretched valuations, positioning, and sentiment. When these conditions occur what is required to bring about a devastating move lower becomes less and less significant. That’s why it’s all the more confounding when massive selloffs happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an interesting common thread to every major crash of the past century- 1929, 1962, and 1987. Each began with pretty mild downward trends which quickly accelerated into crashes. I believe that the market has risen to a position of extreme weakness where it could easily lose its footing and start a similar move down and because of this anything at all can cause it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other warning signs I have been writing about since September- the number of secondary offerings spiking (similar to the launch of additional ARK ETF’s and SPAC’s) shows a public willing to by any old thing that moves. I believe this also explains the recent rally in Bitcoin. Maybe the most damning is the simple fact that so many have seen absurd returns by speculating in equities in recent months. And I’m not talking about 20% gains which the investing public would consider extremely boring today, but 300, 400, even 700% gains in eight or so months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is little doubt to me that in 2021 we will see a major correction in sentiment and price as always must happen when masses with little demonstrated talent suddenly believe themselves to have found a secret gift and should continue to make more money the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to the question of when and how? I mean, who’s to say that even if the market does turn bearish that it isn’t a prolonged, soul-crushing bear market or just a sideways market? Why am I so convinced we will get a crash? It has to do with market levels including valuations, sentiment, and extreme levels of speculation. There have been few (perhaps no) instances where levels got so extended and we didn’t get a major crash. However, many think a correction will come in January. While this could certainly happen, I actually won’t be that surprised to see the market continue this sideways churn for another couple of months to really convince the market that no crash is coming and to not be invested is folly. I’d expect even more IPO’s along the way. More than anything I am looking for a sustained down trend in the market (I use the VALUG on a 4-5% weekly close to define the trend) that looks fairly normal and I would use that to initiate put positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite short ideas are IBM, INTC, DIS and the QQQ’s (within the QQQ’s I’m most bearish on AMZN, MSFT, and CRM). IBM and INTC may seem like odd choices given that this market is defined by extreme speculation in growth stocks, and that given my prior statements I should short shares or buy puts in ARKK. But one thing I learned in the correction in February/March was that stocks exhibit relative weakness for a reason and it isn’t the stocks that rose the most in the bull advance that see the greatest setbacks when the market turns nor the most reluctance to buying on dips. When you are in a major bull market as we have been for the past year or so, stocks like IBM and INTC which have well-defined and understood fundamental problems get buoyed to much higher prices than they probably otherwise would. Additionally, these two stocks have some of the lowest implied volatility making the upside for put options in a crash event much greater than a stock like TSLA or AMZN where the IV is much higher. You can make good money in those as well but your timing has to be exactly right and you may be surprised to learn that you would’ve made even more being positioned in “boring” stocks. In the midst of a crash the high flyers with high IV’s can yield good results if you short counter-trend spikes as people rush in to buy on the dips, but overall these tend to be better tactical very short-term plays. DIS I’m bearish on for a variety of reasons I’ve written about over the past several months ad nauseam so I won’t recount them all here, but one additional factor at play now is the massive rise the stock has seen over the past month on very little fundamental news except for them proclaiming to have won the streaming wars. I’ll believe that when I see it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final point- I don’t believe as some do that we will see a prolonged rotation into small caps or financials with underperformance in megacap tech in 2021. The main reason I continue to point to the fact that megacap tech topped around Labor Day and has been fairly range-bound since is that these stocks defined the bull market of the past several years. I simply don’t believe that the market can have a major advance without them returning to a place of leadership. Small caps have underperformed for years for good reason- they are inferior businesses with inferior leadership. Megacap techs have fantastic fundamentals, ROC, the smartest leadership and the largest TAM’s. When they underperform it’s a major red flag to me. I believe bull markets are strongest when everything works on a relative scale with the best companies leading, particularly at the beginning of a new bull market that few have faith in. That is simply not where we are now. The investing public can make outsized returns for a while but basic laws of survival show that it can’t last and that when it’s going on it in and of itself is a sign something is out of balance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">All crises have involved debt that, in one fashion or another, has become dangerously out of scale in relation to the underlying means of payment. More often, even a semblance of innovation is absent. In the 1920s, as we shall see, great holding companies were created. The owners, that is to say the stockholders, issued bonds and preferred stock in order to buy other stocks. As the latter appreciated in value- for a while- all the increase accrued to the owners. This was proclaimed one of the financial miracles of that age. It was, in fact, leverage in, at most, a slightly different guise.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Markets in 2019</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/04/05/the-markets-in-2019.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Markets in 2019" /><published>2019-04-05T22:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-05T22:31:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/05/the-markets-in-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/04/05/the-markets-in-2019.html">&lt;p&gt;In the process of observing the markets and how they have moved on news over the past year combined with reading several books written over the past 30 years that captured what people knew (or thought they knew) at that time I have developed a sort of unconventional market outlook because I believe that the indicators that used to work no longer do, at least as well as they used to. That shouldn’t be too surprising in and of itself because markets evolve and learn to discount information and then look for the next thing that will tip them off to the future earnings of each company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why cyclicals like Micron start falling when earnings are great and start rising when things are terrible. I’m going to bet that wasn’t always the case. I’d bet that cyclicals at one time actually fell when things started to actually get bad. Then people learned from this and realized that to make a gain you had to make your trade before things started to get bad so the smart money would start taking profits while things were still good. This confuses most observers because people assume that prices should coincide with earnings themselves. But what actually moves the price of the stock is people actually buying and selling it. So those people start dumping to lock in the gains and look to deploy the money elsewhere. Timing this is impossible and most people are very bad at it. In other words they love to buy when it seems there isn’t an end in sight and panic sell when things look like they are terrible and can only get worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I think things have fundamentally changed in some areas and wanted to write them down to see how they hold up in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;An inverted yield curve no longer matters.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think people get way too focused on the inverted yield curve as a recession predictor. I am certain that 50 years ago this would have been an amazing thing to watch if you were clever enough to have done so. But those who were made note of it and the inverted curve became public knowledge and went under a microscope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think people don’t really understand why the inverted curve matters and I would go so far as to say the inversion itself doesn’t even matter besides showing the relative move across different timelines. No two people even seem to agree about what constitutes an inverted curve- the 3 month Treasury Note to 10 year Treasury Bond? Or was it the 2 year to 10 year?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does matter is the trend in short term lending instruments. I like to watch the three month commercial paper rates and think even then it’s just one input and has to be judged in the context of overall rates and how high they are on an absolute basis. Does it really matter if short term rates have been rising if they are sub 3%? That’s still extremely cheap and pretty much ensures that money will be flowing around the economy for a while and there will be no credit crunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The bond markets no longer have any predictive ability.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a pervasive idea that bond markets are smarter than equity markets at analyzing data and predicting changes in the economy. I believe that was definitely true at one point because the bond markets are actually making statements about how much it costs to borrow money across many time horizons. Performing research on fed statements and things that would influence the future costs of borrowing used to be fairly rigorous and most equity traders were more focused on earnings statements than fed statements. Bond traders conversely were far more interested in those in control of monetary policy and then that all would be distilled into the prices of bonds. That’s why equity markets would look to bond markets for predictions about the future price of equities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then along came the internet and Twitter and 24/7 market coverage combined with far more visibility into what the fed and ECB were doing. I believe this eroded any informational advantage the bond markets had. Now the bond markets and equity markets are looking at the exact same things but for some strange reason the equity markets still look to the bond markets to predict future earnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like a student cheating on a test. He may figure with a high degree of certainty that if the smart kid chose “B” as the answer that’s probably the correct answer, but he has no idea why it is. If one day the teacher publishes the multiple choice answers ahead of time but starts grading on essay answers instead, suddenly knowing the correct multiple choice answers has no value and getting the correct responses by copying the smart kid doesn’t add any points to the cheating student’s GPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The next bear market will probably come while rates are still low.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is less of a general market observation and more of a short term prediction for today, but because of the way that markets discount information and the fact that equity markets have now gotten to the point of fully discounting fed policy decisions, people will start dumping stock before the fed makes a monetary decision. I’m still bullish for now, but I do think that equity prices could start falling almost inexplicably while earnings are still good and fed policy is still dovish. While the former would certainly be nothing new, the latter definitely would be. Remember that moving ahead of markets is extraordinarily difficult, some might say impossible, due to the inherent biases we all have and the way we react to how others react to news. I think it’s still possible but you do have to be willing to sell when it seems things can only go higher if the markets start coming down while things seem great. I don’t think the next bear market will be preceded by a major crash, it will be more of a slow bleed down over many months as institutional investors start trimming way out in front of fed policy changes and rotating back into value investments, the same ones that people have hated for the past few years. To me this could happen if inflation were to start ticking up and the market starts anticipating data that would make the fed hawkish and taking profits then instead of after a fed decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternate theory is that we melt up and have a typical blow off the top euphoric market that ends up tumbling down. But since that’s happened pretty recently with the late 90’s bubble and more recently with the housing and bitcoin bubbles, the markets are more attuned to those setups making their actual occurrence less likely. It sounds obvious but its very difficult to sense euphoria in others when its actually happening and not get caught up in it yourself. The same is true for panic. That’s why I find it so absurd when I hear people call for “capitulation selloffs” when markets are trading down as if they actually believe they are more sensible than everyone else and also won’t be in a state of panic when that selloff actually comes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You cannot outperform markets by doing the same thing that everyone else is doing or thinking the same thing that everyone else does. If most people are bullish that will probably work for a while since markets can trend in a direction for a while, but eventually most people won’t come out ahead because when things change they won’t correctly recognize it. I believe that trading is much more game theory than economic theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be okay if you remember these three rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People are almost always wrong. Price action never is.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sentiment always follows price.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cut losses quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In the process of observing the markets and how they have moved on news over the past year combined with reading several books written over the past 30 years that captured what people knew (or thought they knew) at that time I have developed a sort of unconventional market outlook because I believe that the indicators that used to work no longer do, at least as well as they used to. That shouldn’t be too surprising in and of itself because markets evolve and learn to discount information and then look for the next thing that will tip them off to the future earnings of each company.</summary></entry></feed>